Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts at the Clifton Waller Barrett Library of American Literature, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- The Dead Emerson [The Dead Emerson], 1882; uva.00057; xxx.00904; #3829; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder 26)
  This manuscript, entitled The Dead Emerson, contains some handwritten notes about Whitman's last visit (which, according to the manuscript, took place in the winter of 1881) to Ralph Waldo Emerson, and a clipping from a printed piece which is almost equivalent (except for a short phrase) to A Visit, at the Last, to R. W. Emerson as published in Specimen Days in 1882 (retained, within Specimen Days and with the same title, in the Complete Prose Works, published in 1892 ). The clipping included in this manuscript was taken from the section Emerson as He Looks Today which appeared within the article How I Still Get Around at 60, and Take Notes published in the Critic on December 3, 1881.
- I go around among these sights... [I go around], 1860-1863; uva.00097; xxx.00901; xxx.00938; #3829-i; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 45)
  This manuscript is possibly an early draft of another manuscript held at the University of Texas-Austin, entitled "The Army Hospitals." That manuscript was used in the first paragraph of the article The Great Army of the Sick, which was published in the New York Times on February 26, 1863. The contents of both these manuscripts contributed to Feb. 23, published in Memoranda During the War ( 1875-1876 ) and Patent-Office Hospital published in Specimen Days in 1882 (later retained in the Complete Prose Works, published in 1892 ).
- Two Rivulets Two Rivulets, 1875-1876; uva.00072; xxx.00528; #3829; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 14)
  This manuscript is a draft of the Preface to Two Rivulets, published in 1876.
- A tip-top caricature of Walt Whitman [A tip-top caricature of Walt Whitman], 1871-1872; uva.00077; xxx.00880; #3829-h; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 9)
  This manuscript is a draft of a piece, entitled A Tip-Top Caricature of Walt Whitman, about the creation of a new "burlesque portrait" of Whitman by artist Frank Bellew. According to Joel Myerson, the article was published in the Washington Evening Star on November 22, 1872. According to Emory Holloway, the caricature by Bellew was published in the Fifth Avenue Journal in 1872.
- The Bible as Poetry [I suppose one can say], 1880-1883; uva.00084; xxx.00810; xxx.00460; #3829-i; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 10)
  This manuscript is an early draft of the first part of the essay "The Bible as Poetry" published in the Critic on February 3, 1883 and then included, with the same title, in November Boughs, published in 1888 (later retained in the Complete Prose Works, published in 1892 ). On the verso is a letter from D.W. Zimmerman to Whitman, dated 13 January 1883.
- Of Biography and of all literature and art [Of Biography], 1857-1859; uva.00100; xxx.00240; #3829-i; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 64)
  This manuscript contains a note composed around 1857-1859. It contains two phrases ("authors who considered their subject with reference to the ensemble of the world"; "every subject has been made too prononce' ") that are resonant with passages of the poem Laws for Creation first published in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass and later retained in all subsequent editions of Leaves of Grass.
- A Night Battle, Over a Week Since [Who shall tell], 1862-1875; uva.00107; xxx.00902; #3829-i; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 62)
  This manuscript is a draft of A Night Battle, over a Week Since published first in Memoranda During the War in 1876 and then (with the same title) in Specimen Days in 1882 (later retained in Complete Prose Works, published in 1892 ).
- How I made a book How I made a book, 1885-1886; uva.00148; xxx.00410; #3829-f; prose 34 leaves handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder 43)
  This manuscript is a draft of the essay How I Made a Book, published in the Philadelphia Press on July 11, 1886 and later included in Democratic Vistas, and Other Papers published in 1888. The manuscript also contains two clippings (with handwritten revisions) of the essay A Backward Glance on My Own Road, published in the Critic on January 5, 1884. (This latter essay was revised and also included in Democratic Vistas, and Other Papers published in 1888 ). How I Made a Book, A Backward Glance on my Own Road and My Book and I (which was published in Lippincott's Magazine on January 1887 and later included in Democratic Vistas, and Other Papers published in 1888 ) all contributed to form the essay A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads which was published in November Boughs in 1888 and later retained in the 1892 edition of Leaves of Grass.
- The Dead Carlyle The Dead Carlyle, 1881; uva.00151; xxx.00885; #3829-i; prose 3 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 25)
  This manuscript is a draft of the essay The Dead Carlyle printed in the Literary World on February 12, 1881 and, with the slightly different title of The Death of Carlyle in the Critic, on February 12, 1881. Parts of the essay were used for Death of Thomas Carlyle published in Specimen Days in 1882 (later retained in the Complete Prose Works, published in 1892 ).
- Walt Whitman is putting the later touches... [Walt Whitman is putting the later touches], 1890; uva.00395; xxx.00903; #3829-i; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 19)
  This manuscript contains part of an autobiographical sketch on the composition of Good-bye My Fancy. At the top left of the manuscript is the date November 10, 1890. The article based on this draft was published in the Critic on November 29, 1890 as On Good-Bye My Fancy. The article had been prompted by the editors of the Critic with a letter of November 1, 1890 seen on the verso of the manuscript.
- "And that was war..." [And that was war], 1862-1876; uva.00396; xxx.00902; #3829-ac; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 2-a)
  This manuscript contains a passage about a war night scene of "flitting souls" which would appear, with revisions and additions, with the title of A Night Battle, Over a Week Since in Memoranda During the War in 1876 (later retained in Complete Prose Works, published in 1892 ).
- Last of the War Cases [There has been [Washington, Oct. 13, 1863]], uva.00409; xxx.00485; #3829-h; prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 1, Folder 48)
  This manuscript is a partial draft of Last of the War Cases, first published in November Boughs in 1888 and later in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- J.B. Gilder to [Walt] Whitman, 1887 March 17 [Camden March 18], uva.00475; xxx.00899; #3829-i; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder 72)
  This manuscript is a response to a letter of March 17, 1887 from Joseph B. Gilder, editor of the Critic. In the letter, Gilder asked Whitman if he agreed to publish a short note about the letter that the poet had recently received from Alfred Tennyson. (Tennyson had responded to Whitman's A Word About Tennyson, published in the Critic on January 1, 1887 ). Whitman agreed to the publication of such a note, followed by his ideas on how to phrase it. The note, based closely on Whitman's suggested phrasing, was published first in the Critic on March 26, 1887 and then in The Literary World on April 8, 1887.
- [New York visit], 1878; uva.00480; xxx.00916; xxx.00917; #3829-i; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 38)
  This manuscript is a draft of A Poet's Recreation published in the New York Daily Tribune on July 4, 1878. The essay was reprinted with revisions as Death of William Cullen Bryant in Specimen Days in 1882. The manuscript is pasted down, making the verso inaccessible.
- Out West not Long Since, 1880-1882; uva.00488; xxx.00918; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  This manuscript is a partial draft of A Week's Visit to Boston published in Specimen Days in 1882.
- The Soul's Procession The Soul's Procession, 1869-1871; uva.00121; xxx.00496; #5604; poetry prose 16 leaves handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder 93)
  This handmade notebook contains notes for a projected poem, The Soul's Procession, as well as a newspaper clipping attached to the third leaf, entitled The Steamship Pereire Disaster and dated January 28, 1869. Whitman never finished or published this poem, but various passages are similar to ideas and language in the poem Passage to India, first published in the 1871-1872 edition of Leaves of Grass and retained in all subsequent editions.
- Leaves of Grass & Two Rivulets: Draft of Advertisement for Centennial Edition, 1876 [Centennial Ed'n], 1870-1876; uva.00163; xxx.00905; #3829-a.; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder 53)
  This manuscript is a draft for the advertisement, with information about price, binding, and contents, for the "Centennial Edition" of Leaves of Grass, published in 1876 The manuscript is almost identical (with the exception of the expression "Italian card" instead of "Italian boards") to a manuscript preserved in Harned collection (see loc.05636).
- Brutish human beings - wild men - the 'koboo' Brutish human beings, 1857-1859; uva.00085; xxx.00048; xxx.00110; #3829-i; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder 12)
  This manuscript contains notes by Whitman about what he calls "a very low kind of human beings," "wild men," the "koboo," apparently described to Whitman by Elias Pierson in June 1857. Pierson had been to China in the rebel army of Canton, and had seen the aboriginal "koboo" people, as reported in the manuscript, in the Ladrone islands, in the South China Sea off Canton. To reinforce the truthfulness of Pierson's stories about the "koboo," Whitman mentions the fact that Captain Walter Murray Gibson, who had also talked about the "koboo" people (possibly in the book Report, American Geographical and Statistical Society. Monthly Meeting. March, 1854. Captain Walter M. Gibson on the East Indian Archipelago: a Description of Its Wild Races of Men, published in 1854, and/or in The Prison of Weltevredin, and a Glance at the East Indian Archipelago, published in 1855), had affirmed that all his statements in the book were true and made in good faith. Since the term "koboo" is used by Whitman in Song of Myself (the term already appeared in the first published version of the poem, in the 1855 edition, and was retained in all the subsequent editions) and in Salut au Monde! (the term appeared in the first published version of the poem in the 1856 edition and was retained in all the subsequent editions), it is probable that Whitman first learned about the "koboo" by reading Gibson, and then heard again about them from Pierson. The manuscript also contains a clipping of a short newspaper column entitled "The Wild Men of Borneo," and a short comment on it.
- Glimpses of Walt Whitman The voice is a curious organ, 1850-1855; uva.00477; xxx.00908; xxx.00909; #3829-i; prose 1 handwritten printed (Box 1, Folder 38)
  This manuscript scrap might be part of the missing page 8 in another manuscript by Whitman, A Visit to the Opera, held at the Huntington Library. This latter piece, together with other manuscripts about opera singing, contributed to form the article The Opera, published in Life Illustrated on November 10, 1855. For a full explanation of the intricacies of these various manuscripts, see: Edward Grier. Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts (New York: New York University Press, 1984) 1:388-398. The manuscript is pasted down, making the verso inaccessible.